Herman Wolf Papers 1985.0008
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Herman Wolf Papers
undated, 1926-1981
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1985.0008
117 Linear Feet
Born in New York in 1912; graduated in 1933 with a B. A. in Economics from the University of Chicago; was actively involved in political journalism from 1934 to 1941; operated several public-relations firms, including Herman Wolf Associates; served as a chief campaign aide for many successful campaigns for offices; member of the National Press Club, the Public Relations Society of America, and the Bridgeport Chamber of Commerce.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The materials were donated by Herman Wolf in December 1985.
Arrangement
Series I: Gubernatorial Politics (undated, 1949-1980) contains files on gubernatorial candidates in Connecticut. The materials include biographical files, policy information, debate transcripts, pamphlets, and news clippings on candidates such as Abraham Ribicoff, Emilio Daddario and Ella Grasso. The series is arranged chronologically and by candidate.
Series II: Congressional Politics (undated, 1948-1980) includes campaign materials, pamphlets, speeches, and correspondence on candidates such as Dennis Carrol, William St. Onge and Ella Grasso. The series is arranged chronologically and by candidate.
Series III: Senatorial Politics (undated, 1950-1976) includes campaign materials, correspondence, news clippings and platforms of candidates for Connecticut State positions. Included are William Benton, Thomas Dodd, Abraham Ribicoff, and others. The series is arranged chronologically and by candidate.
Series IV: Connecticut Town Politics (undated, 1966-1975) includes advertising materials and debate transcripts from the Fairfield, CT, mayoral elections of John Sullivan, as well as campaign summaries of local elections in Connecticut cities and towns. The town files are arranged alphabetically.
Series V: Bridgeport: Curran Administration (undated, 1964-1973) focuses on Bridgeport politics. It includes biographical information on Mayor Curran, his speeches, addresses and press releases, photographs, and campaign materials. There is also information on the P. T. Barnum Festival, the Bridgeport Jets, the University of Bridgeport, and the Proud City Campaign. The series is arranged chronologically.
Series VI: Connecticut Democratic Party (undated, 1950-1980) contains information on state politics. Included are campaign material; correspondence; materials from the Democratic National Conventions, 1960-1968; materials from the Democratic State Central Committee; files on Hubert Humphrey, John F.Kennedy and the Kennedy family; files on the Republican National Committee; and state convention information. This series is arranged alphabetically.
Series VII: Ways To Win (undated, 1940s-1980) contains materials related to Wolf's proposed book, Ways to Win, which covered public relations efforts on behalf of political candidates. The series focuses on Wolf's 1968 Newspaper Project, with survey information, ads, target newspapers, and a newspaper advertising book outline. Also included in the series are public relations subject folders with information on billboards, campaign planning, image, media contacts, news releases, polls, radio campaigning, and volunteers. There is also a nineteen state candidate survey, and a house and senate candidate file which includes information on Robert Giaimo, Stewart McKinney, Horace Seely Brown, Christopher Dodd, Daniel Inouye, and Lowell Weicker. The series is arranged alphabetically.
Series VIII: Public Relations (undated, 1950-1981) contains materials from Wolf's non-politician public relations work, including information about the American Association of Advertising Agencies, the Bureau of Advertising, and the U. S. Chamber of Commerce. Advertising rates, fund raising, radio campaigning, and women in politics are some of the subjects in this series. The files are arranged alphabetically.
Series IX: Political Organizations (undated, 1926-1980) includes files on numerous organizations, including the Steering Committee on Human Rights Legislation, the American Civil Liberties Union, Americans for Democratic Action, Common Cause, the Hartford Jewish Federation, the National Urban League, the Rand School of Social Science, the Socialist Party, and the World Peace Foundation. The files are arranged alphabetically. This series also contains files of awards, dinners, testimonials, and ceremonies for politician figures, including Thomas Dodd, Ella Grasso, and Abraham Ribicoff.
Series X: National Politics (undated, 1936-1976) contains material on Alfred Landon, Franklin D. Roosevelt, the American Labor Party, Adlai Stevenson, John Kennedy, Richard Nixon, Barry Goldwater, Eugene McCarthy, George McGovern, Ronald Reagan, George Wallace, and Jimmy Carter.
Series XI: Personal Papers (undated, 1941-1981) has been arranged under six subheadings: Alaska Federation of Natives, American Shakespeare Theatre, Bridgeport Jets, General Correspondence, Labor, and Subject Files. Alaska Federation of Natives contains brochures, pamphlets, project financing reports, and land claim bills concerning Native Alaskans' rights and the Alaska pipeline. American Shakespeare Theatre contains public relations' materials for the Stratford theatre, including advertising, correspondence, photographs, promotional materials, and theatre publications. Bridgeport Jets contains promotional materials such as buttons, press clippings and releases, and graphics. General Correspondence consists of folders of Wolf's correspondence arranged chronologically. Labor contains AFL-CIO materials, AFL candidate questionnaires and statements, local Labor Council correspondence, ILGW files, and labor reports. Subject Files is listed alphabetically, and includes information on AVCO; the Bottle Bill; cattle breeding; civil rights; Doubleday; Savings Bank Association of America; the State Police; and Herman Wolf's father, Irving Wolf.
Series XII: Memorabilia (undated, 1936-1968) contains both written materials and items from Wolf's years of involvement in politics, including posters, campaign buttons and flyers, bumper stickers, news clippings, and photographs. There is memorabilia from World War II; local, state and national elections; from well-known politicians such as Abraham Ribicoff, John F. Kennedy, Audrey Beck, and Ella Grasso>, as well as senate passes, inaugural invitations, and scrapbooks containing news clippings and election headlines.
Series XIII: Publications (undated, 1940s-1969) contains newsletters, journals, and reports from military, labor, and social organizations. The files are arranged alphabetically.
Series XIV: Audio Visual Materials (undated, 1950s-1975) contains interviews, radio spots, television advertisements from Connecticut and national political campaigns.
Biography
Herman Wolf was born in Far Rockaway, Long Island, New York on 22 January 1912. He graduated from the Woodmere Academy in Long Island in 1929. After attending the Wharton School at the University of Pennsylvania for two years, he spent one year at the University of Chicago from which he graduated in 1933 with a B. A. in Economics. From 1935 to 1939 he attended the New School for Social Research in New York, as well as New York University.
As a young man, Wolf was deeply interested in reform movements, and while at the University of Pennsylvania was an active member of the Socialist Party. From 1934-1941, Wolf was a labor newspaper editor and publicity agent. He wrote publicity articles, speeches, press releases, radio broadcasts, and pamphlets for such organizations as the Textile Workers Union, the International Ladies Garment Workers' Union, the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America, the American Labor Party, the New York State Department of Labor, and the Greater New York Fund. He also spent some time editing weekly newspapers, working on the New York Journal of Commerce, and writing articles for Time, Nation, and Survey Graphic. From 1937-1941, he operated his own public relations firm in New York City.
During the Second World War, Wolf's governmental employment was extensive. He directed labor-public relations for the British Management-Labor Commission, wrote a war handbook entitled Labor Defends America, a discussion of labor's role in production, morale, war controls, and training, promoted U.S. War Bonds for the Treasury Department in his writings for the labor press, and directed a staff of fifteen for the War Production Board which supplied 5,000 war plant Labor-Management Production Committees with ideas and material for improving efficiency.
After the war, Wolf spent two years as a director of a staff of seventy employees for the Fuller Houses Inc. of Wichita, Kansas, a corporation created to promote the building of R. Buckminster Fuller's Dymaxion Dwelling Machine (the Fuller House). This began a longtime association between Wolf and Fuller.
In 1946, Wolf moved to Connecticut and began a public-relations firm, Herman Wolf Associates, that would eventually serve over 100 clients. From 1947-1950, he was editor of several of the supplements for the Sunday edition of The Bridgeport Herald. It was at this time that Wolf became actively involved in Connecticut Democratic politics. He was a chief campaign aide in the successful gubernatorial campaigns of Abe Ribicoff in 1954 and 1958, John Dempsey in 1966, and Ella Grasso in 1974. He acted as executive aide to Governor Ribicoff from 1955-1958, and took part in Ribicoff's successful campaigns for the U. S. Senate in 1962 and 1968.
Herman Wolf participated actively in numerous campaigns for Senate, Congress, state legislature, and municipal office over a period of thirty years. In the course of his political public relations work, he met seven Presidents of the United States.
In 1972, Wolf closed down his public relations firm for a brief time to become Executive Vice-President of the Design Science Institute of Washington D. C., a nonprofit organization dedicated to advancing the philosophy and works of R. Buckminster Fuller. Wolf iwas a member of the National Press Club, the Public Relations Society of America, and the Bridgeport Chamber of Commerce. His first wife, Emily Elsas Wolf, whom he married in 1936, died in 1954. They had three children: David, born in 1942; Louise, born in 1944; and William (Bill), born in 1949. His second wife was Helen Neilson Wolf. In 1973, Wolf married Monica Estes. They have one daughter, Fay, born in 1978.
Scope and Content
The Herman Wolf Papers document the career of Herman Wolf from the early 1940s through the late 1980s. Spanning forty years of local, state, and national politics, Wolf's papers provide a unique view of the political scene, from Connecticut gubernatorial politics in 1949 to the presidential election in 1976. Wolf's papers concerning Buckminster Fuller are in a separate collection in this repository. Most of his papers concerning organized labor were donated to the Walter Reuther Library, Wayne State University.
Public relations.; Petitions; Posters; Speeches (documents); Obituaries; Typescripts; Galley proofs; Press releases; Actions and defenses; Administrative records; Financial Records; Publications (documents); Oral histories (document genres); Photographs; Audiocassettes; Audio visual materials; Videocassettes; Interviews; Monographs; Correspondence; Notebooks; Manuscripts (document genre); Notes; Photocopies; Daddario, Emilio Q. (Emilio Quincy), 1918-2010; Ribicoff, Abraham, 1910-1988
- Series I: Gubernatorial Politics, undated, 1949-1980
  - Bowles, Chester
    - 1949-1957 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
  - Ribicoff, Abraham, 1954-1962
    - Biographical file (Box 1)
    - Campaign correspondence, 1952-1970 (Box 1)
    - CIO-PAC (Box 1)
    - Connecticut tourism
    - DSCC: campaign book and platform, 1954
    - Inaugural message, 1955
    - Lodge, John, 1954
    - Mailings to governor's office, 1957-1958
    - Pamphlets, 1954-1961
    - Ad Slogans
    - Press clippings, 1953-1971
    - Press releases, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Radio speeches (Box 1)
    - Statements: John Dempsey, Sam Tedesco, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Television speeches, 1954-1968 (Box 1)
    - War record charges, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Dempsey, John, 1960-1966
    - Addresses, 1961-1966 (Box 1)
    - Biographical file, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Committee for Dempsey, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Connecticut Moves Ahead for Progress Program, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1955-1970 (Box 1)
    - Editorial excerpts (Box 1)
    - Gengras, E. Clayton (Box 1)
    - Newsclippings (Box 1)
    - Editorials on Dempsey campaign (Box 1)
    - Highway safety (Box 1)
    - Legislative record, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Letter (Box 1)
    - Media (Box 1)
    - News clippings (Box 1)
    - Photographs, 1962-1968 (Box 1)
    - Policies
      - Education (Box 1)
      - Fiscal (Box 1)
    - Public protection and safety (Box 1)
    - Press releases, 1961-1966 (Box 2)
    - Printed campaign materials (Box 2)
    - Public relations: Randall Company (Box 2)
    - Radio and television addresses (Box 2)
    - Votemobile
      - Printed materials (Box 2)
      - Public relations (Box 2)
      - Silver Anvil Award (Box 2)
      - Schedules of appearances and notes (Box 2)
  - Daddario, Emilio, 1970
    - Abortion (Box 2)
    - Advertisements (Box 2)
    - Campaign correspondence (Box 2)
    - Campaign notes and memos (Box 2)
    - Campaign staff research (Box 2)
    - Comparisons (Box 2)
    - Congressional reports (Box 2)
    - Connecticut candidates list (Box 2)
    - Crime (Box 2)
    - Debates/statements (Box 2)
    - Fact sheets (Box 2)
    - Flyer (Box 2)
    - Flyers (Box 2)
    - Fuel (Box 2)
    - Guns (Box 2)
    - Hi-Ho Construction Company (Box 2)
    - Labor/unemployment (Box 2)
    - Meskill, Thomas file (Box 2)
    - News clippings (Box 2)
    - News releases (Box 2)
    - Pamphets (Box 2)
    - Panel discussion (Box 2)
    - Photographs (Box 2)
    - Policy statements (Box 2)
    - Polls (Box 2)
    - Radio and television (Box 2)
    - Railroad and public transportation, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Republicans for Daddario (Box 3)
    - Speeches, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Television commercials, inlcudes two slides, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Television final (Box 3)
  - Grasso, Ella, 1974
    - Acceptance Speech (Box 3)
    - AFL-CIO COPE (Box 3)
    - Biographical file (Box 3)
    - Campaign advertising, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Campaign contributions and expenditures, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Campaign finances (Box 3)
    - Campaign notes: Wolf (Box 3)
    - Connecticut Business and Industry Association (CBIA) (Box 4)
    - Connecticut Citizens Action and Research Group (Box 4)
    - Connecticut state election calendar (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
    - Democratic Party for Grasso Committee (Box 4)
    - Economic issues: research data (Box 4)
    - Endorsements (Box 4)
    - Fairfield County Committee for Ella Grasso (Box 4)
    - Finance Committee (Box 4)
    - Grasso For Governor (Box 4)
    - Income tax statement (Box 4)
    - League of Women Voters (Box 4)
    - Media and political advertising (Box 4)
    - News clippings (Box 4)
    - News releases (Box 4)
    - Pamphlets (Box 4)
    - Photographs (Box 4)
    - Political opponents
      - Babbidge, Homer (Box 4)
      - Kilian, Robert (Box 4)
      - Lufkin, Dan (Box 4)
      - Sarasin, Ronald (Box 4)
      - Steele, Robert (Box 4)
      - Zullo, Frank (Box 4)
    - Primary calendar (Box 4)
    - Public utilities (Box 5)
    - Radio (Box 5)
    - Republican State Central Committee (Box 5)
    - Singles tax bill: Vivien Kellems (Box 5)
    - Speeches (Box 5)
    - State Legislative Appearance Registration (Box 5)
    - Statements (Box 5)
    - Sullivan, John, Lt. Governor (Box 5)
    - Television (Box 5)
    - Time/Newsweek (Box 5)
    - Voting records (Box 5)
    - Voting registration (Box 5)
- Series II: Congressional Politics, undated, 1948-1980
  - Carrol, Dennis, 1948-1950
    - Biographical file, 1950 (Box 6)
    - Campaign contributions, 1950 (Box 6)
    - Campaign correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 6)
    - Campaign expenses, 1950 (Box 6)
    - Danbury Committee for Carol, 1950 (Box 6)
    - News clippings, 1950 (Box 6)
    - Pamphlets, 1950 (Box 6)
    - Speeches, 1950 (Box 6)
  - Daddario, Emilio, 1960-1966
    - Pamphlets and reports (Box 6)
    - Opponent: Tom Brennan (Box 6)
  - Kowakski, Frank, 1958-1966
    - Correspondence and notes, 1960-1962 (Box 6)
    - Pamphlets and press clippings, 1958-1966 (Box 6)
  - St. Onge, William, 1960-1968
    - Artwork, campaign notes, correspondence, 1960-1968 (Box 6)
    - Billboards, 1966-1968 (Box 6)
    - Campaign expenses, 1966-1968 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Newspaper and radio advertising, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
    - News releases, 1965-1966 (Box 6)
    - Pamphlets, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Radio campaign, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Campaign expenses, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Newspaper advertising, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Radio, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Pamphlets, 1968 (Box 6)
  - Grasso, Ella, 1970-1974
    - Campaign (Box 6)
    - Campaign preparations (Box 6)
    - Congressional record (Box 6)
    - Correspondence (Box 6)
    - Flyers (Box 6)
    - Opponent: Richard Kilbourne's campaign strategy (Box 6)
  - Daly, Roy, 1970 (Box 6)
  - Konitshek, Wayne, 1979-1980
    - Correspondence (Box 6)
    - Opponent: John Phillips (Box 6)
    - Pamphlets (Box 6)
    - Photographs (Box 6)
    - Press clippings (Box 6)
- Series III: Senatorial Politics, 1950-1976
  - Benton, William, 1950-1974 (Box 7)
  - Dodd, Thomas J., 1954-1968
    - Campaign pamphlets (Box 7)
    - Correspondence and notes, 1954-1968 (Box 7)
    - News clippings, 1960-1968 (Box 7)
    - Testimonial dinner, 1958-1961 (Box 7)
  - Donahue, Al, 1958-1961 (Box 7)
  - Duffy, Joseph (Box 7)
  - Ribicoff, Abraham, 1962-1979
    - Campaign advertising (Box 8)
    - Campaign contributions, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Campaign notes: Wolf, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Congressional record, 1965-1980 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1977 (Box 8)
    - Invitations, 1954-1974 (Box 8)
    - News clippings, 1954-1980 (Box 8)
    - Pamphlets, 1954-1973 (Box 8)
    - Photographs, 1964-1968 (Box 8)
    - Platforms
      - Agriculture (Box 8)
      - Business (Box 8)
      - Cities (Box 8)
      - Civil rights (Box 8)
      - Conservation (Box 8)
      - Consumer protection (Box 8)
      - Defense (Box 8)
      - Economy (Box 8)
      - Education (Box 8)
      - Efficiency on government (Box 8)
      - Foreign policy (Box 8)
      - Labor (Box 8)
      - Law enforcement (Box 8)
      - Poverty (Box 8)
      - Social sciences (Box 8)
      - Science and technology (Box 8)
      - Taxation (Box 8)
      - Traffic safety (Box 8)
      - Transportation (Box 8)
      - Veterans (Box 8)
      - Viet Nam (Box 8)
      - Youth Safety Camp (Box 8)
    - Press releases, 1954-1980 (Box 8)
    - Republicans for Ribicoff (Box 8)
    - Seeley-Brown, Horace (Box 8)
    - Speeches, 1962-1976 (Box 8)
    - Telethon, 1968 (Box 8)
    - UPI dispatches (Box 8)
    - Voter Analysis, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Voter Data, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Voter information: town, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Schaffer, Gloria, 1969-1976
    - Correspondence and notes (Box 8)
    - Pamphlets (Box 8)
    - Press clippings (Box 8)
- Series IV: Connecticut Town Politics, undated, 1960-1980
  - Local Politics
    - Campaign expenses, 1967-1969 (Box 9)
    - Campaign summary, 1967 (Box 9)
    - City editors (Box 9)
    - "City Hall News", 1966 (Box 9)
    - Democratic chairmen and districts (Box 9)
    - Education grants, 1970 (Box 9)
    - Municipal budgets (Box 9)
    - Municipal city government (Box 9)
    - Photographs (Box 9)
    - Radio, 1969-1978 (Box 9)
    - Registered democrats (Box 9)
    - State Senate and Assembly: candidate flyers, 1960-1974 (Box 9)
    - Town information A - Z (Box 9)
  - Connecticut Town Politics
    - Avon (Box 9)
    - Bethel (Box 9)
    - Bloomfield (Box 9)
    - Bridgeport (Box 9)
    - Clinton (Box 9)
    - Danbury (Box 9)
    - East Hampton (Box 9)
    - Fairfield (Box 9)
    - Fairfield: John Sullivan, 1969-1975 (Box 10)
      - Advertising, 1969 (Box 10)
      - Candidate debate, 1969 (Box 10)
      - Campaign correspondence, 1968-1975 (Box 10)
      - Campaign Expenses, 1969-1973 (Box 10)
      - Letters to voters, 1969 (Box 10)
      - Pamphlets, 1969-1975 (Box 10)
      - Photographs, 1969 (Box 10)
      - Press releases, 1969 (Box 10)
      - Radio advertising, 1963-1969 (Box 10)
      - Statistics, 1968 (Box 10)
    - Farmington (Box 10)
    - Goshen (Box 10)
    - Greenwich (Box 10)
    - Hartford (Box 10)
    - West Hartford (Box 10)
    - Hartland-Newington-North Hartford (Box 10)
    - Mansfield (Box 10)
    - Meriden (Box 10)
    - Middletown (Box 10)
    - Milford (Box 10)
    - New Britain (Box 11)
    - New Haven (Box 11)
    - Newington (Box 11)
    - Norwalk (Box 11)
    - Saybrook (Box 11)
    - Simsbury (Box 11)
    - Salisbury (Box 11)
    - Somers (Box 11)
    - Stamford (Box 11)
    - Stratford (Box 11)
    - Tolland (Box 11)
    - Torrington (Box 11)
    - Westchester (Box 11)
    - West Haven (Box 11)
    - Weston (Box 11)
    - Westport (Box 11)
    - Westfield-Middlesex (Box 11)
    - Williams County (Box 11)
    - Willimantic (Box 11)
- Series V: Bridgeport: Curran Administration, undated, 1964-1973
  - Newspaper clippings, 1964-1973 (Box 12)
  - 1965
    - Biannual message to Common Council (Box 12)
    - Biography (Box 12)
    - City of All America (Box 12)
    - Democratic platform (Box 12)
    - Major talks and topics (Box 12)
    - News releases (Box 12)
    - Newspaper advertising schedule (Box 12)
    - Press releases (Box 12)
    - Proposals and initiatives (Box 12)
    - Radio spots (Box 12)
    - Republicans and independents (Box 12)
    - Research (Box 12)
    - Speaking schedule (Box 12)
    - Speeches (Box 12)
    - Today section (Box 12)
    - University of Bridgeport (Box 12)
    - Young Democrats (Box 12)
  - 1966
    - New York Times: CT supplement (Box 12)
    - Photographs (Box 12)
    - Rooster River Flood Control Project (Box 12)
    - State of the City (Box 12)
  - 1967
    - Annual financial report (Box 12)
    - Campaign memos (Box 12)
    - Chamber of Commerce (Box 12)
    - Connecticut Circle Magazine (Box 12)
    - Council message (Box 12)
    - Democratic Town Committee (Box 12)
    - Letters to Democratic voters (Box 12)
    - Mayor's Conference on Housing (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
    - News releases (Box 12)
    - Photographs (Box 12)
    - Profile (Box 12)
    - Radio and television ads (Box 12)
    - Speeches (Box 12)
    - Speeches and releases (Box 13)
    - State Senatorial campaign (Box 13)
    - Testimonial dinner (Box 13)
    - University of Bridgeport speech (Box 13)
  - 1968
    - Anti-litter (Box 13)
    - Barnum Festival (Box 13)
    - Biography (Box 13)
    - Bridgeport Jets (Box 13)
    - Campaigns (Box 13)
    - Chamber of Commerce (Box 13)
    - Charter revision (Box 13)
    - Computer personnel release (Box 13)
    - Construction (Box 13)
    - Correspondence (Box 13)
    - Danenberg, Leigh (Box 13)
    - Fairfield University (Box 13)
    - Festival Theatre (Box 13)
    - First Regional Meeting (Box 13)
    - House of Representative campaigns (Box 13)
    - Job tree (Box 13)
    - Junior Chamber of Commerce (Box 13)
    - King, Martin Luther (Box 13)
    - King Cole: liquor license (Box 13)
    - Lafayette Mall (Box 13)
    - Local buildings (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
    - Parks (Box 13)
    - Proclamation: Bridgeport Elks (Box 13)
    - Proclamations (Box 13)
    - Proud City Campaign (Box 13)
    - Public Information Office (Box 13)
    - Route 25 (Box 13)
    - Sacred Heart University (Box 13)